<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>mental Scrapheap</title><link>http://localhost:8000/</link><description>Where all that mental junk gets piled up</description><atom:link href="http://localhost:8000/feeds/rick-veenstra.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>Lessons from Benjamin Zanders' talk on TED 2008</title><link>http://localhost:8000/2013/02/lessons-from-benjamin-zanders-talk-on-ted-2008/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Benjamin Zander is a world-famous classical orchestra conductor.
During his talk at TED2008 on 'classical music and passion' he refers to
a moment of 'enlightenment' as I would call it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was 45 years old, I'd been conducting for 20 years, and I suddenly
had a realization. The conductor of an orchestra doesn't make a
sound. (...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He depends, for his power, on his ability to make other people
powerful. And that changed everything for me. It was totally life
changing. (...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized my job was to awaken possibility in other people. And of
course, I wanted to know whether I was doing that. And you know how
you find out? You look at their eyes. If their eyes are shining, you
know you're doing it. (...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the eyes are not shining, you get to ask a question. And this is
the question: who am I being, that my players' eyes are not shining?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wow, now that's what I would call enlightenment. &amp;quot;My job is to awaken
possibility is other people&amp;quot;. That resonates with me, deep inside.
Servant leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benjamin extends this insight to parenthood, generalizes this to his
vision of succes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can do that with our children, too. Who am I being, that my
children's eyes are not shining? That's a totally different world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you know, I have a definition of success. For me, it's very
simple. It's not about wealth and fame and power. It's about how
many shining eyes I have around me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice how he phrases this. It's not &amp;quot;how am I &lt;em&gt;behaving&lt;/em&gt;, that their
eyes are not shining?&amp;quot; but &amp;quot;how am I &lt;strong&gt;being&lt;/strong&gt;?&amp;quot; That's a far deeper way
to look at it. Fundamental. Existential. &amp;quot;Who am I &lt;strong&gt;being&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;? Who can I
&lt;strong&gt;be&lt;/strong&gt; for others so that their eyes are shining?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This question shifts our focus. It's not primarily about &lt;strong&gt;doing&lt;/strong&gt;, it's
all about &lt;strong&gt;being&lt;/strong&gt;. Because who we are is the source of our doing. Our
identity, our views of who we are and our purpose in life, is the driver
for all that we do. It also shifts our focus from ourselves to the
other. Though we ask what &lt;strong&gt;we&lt;/strong&gt; are being, we define that in terms of
our impact on others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who am I being...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that my spouse's eyes are not shining?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that my children's eyes are not shining?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that my colleague's eyes are not shining?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that my team's eyes are not shining?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that my congregation's eyes are not shining?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and we can extend this question to each and every relation we have in
this life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Rick Veenstra</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:localhost:8000,2013-02-09:2013/02/lessons-from-benjamin-zanders-talk-on-ted-2008/</guid><category>ted</category><category>faith</category></item><item><title>TheRobertD interviews Farnoosh Brock</title><link>http://localhost:8000/2013/02/therobertd-interviews-farnoosh-brock/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Robert D. Smith a.k.a. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://therobertd.com"&gt;The Robert D.&lt;/a&gt; (twitter:&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/therobertd"&gt;&amp;#64;TheRobertD&lt;/a&gt;) has done an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://therobertd.us2.list-manage.com/track/click?u=c96aa46d674ff7d7033d8c432&amp;amp;id=1a60c072fd&amp;amp;e=81cbc06ea9"&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; with Farnoosh Brock
of the &amp;quot;amazing website&amp;quot; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://prolificliving.com"&gt;ProlificLiving.com&lt;/a&gt;, for three reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There’s a ton you and I can learn from how she built such an amazing website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Over the past few years, she has built such a successful business that she hasn’t wasted a single second regretting her decision to leave a six-figure corporate job behind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She creates an INSANE amount of value for anyone willing to invest their time/money in anything she releases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The warning that &amp;quot;you might want to leave your day job immediately&amp;quot; is a litle bit worrisome, coming from somebody
like Robert. I've not yet explored the site; from the outside it looks slick and promising. But as the old english proverb says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The proof of the pudding is in the eating&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and though dinner is served, I've not yet tasted it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Rick Veenstra</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:localhost:8000,2013-02-06:2013/02/therobertd-interviews-farnoosh-brock/</guid><category>Personal effectivity</category><category>links</category></item><item><title>Now</title><link>http://localhost:8000/2013/01/now/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday is closed, finished, done. Nothing can be changed about what is passed. Whatever has happened stays happened. Forever. Only our memories can change. And they &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; change, that's for sure. Because every time we revisit a memory we are in fact &lt;em&gt;re-creating&lt;/em&gt; it, &lt;em&gt;re-shaping&lt;/em&gt; it, changing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow is uncertain. What we 'know for sure' about tomorrow is nothing more than an extrapolation of our past experiences. Which are uncertain by themselves, since our memories are volatile and unreliable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Yesterday is a memory, tomorrow is a dream; today is a gift, that's why it's called &amp;quot;present&amp;quot;.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only thing we have is today, now. Actually not even that much; all we have is just this very moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter the circumstances or events that got us here. No matter whether we like it or not. No matter the path behind us or the path before us. We are right here, right now, and that's all we have. That's what we have to deal with, that's what we have to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;these circumstances; comfortable, hard or even painful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;these people, whether we like them or not&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this task, this job, this resonsibility, this opportunity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever we may posess, whatever influence we may think we have, bottom line is that we have very little. Just now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Now what? What are you going to do with what you do have?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;There's nothin' behind me and nothin' that ties me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;To somethin' that might have been true yesterday&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tomorrow is open, right now it seems to be more than enough&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;to just be here today&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.metrolyrics.com/sweet-surrender-lyrics-john-denver.html"&gt;John Denver - Sweet Surrender&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Rick Veenstra</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2013 21:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:localhost:8000,2013-01-28:2013/01/now/</guid><category>quotes</category></item><item><title>Every successful enterprise requires three men...</title><link>http://localhost:8000/2013/01/Every_successful_enterprise_requires_three_men/</link><description>&lt;!--  --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Every successful enterprise requires three men - a
dreamer, a businessman and a son-of-a-bitch&amp;quot; -Peter MacArthur&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/ptarkkonen/status/295095179155742720"&gt;Tweet from Petteri Tarkkonen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quote suggests that there are several distinct roles that have to
be present in a group for any endeavour to be succesfull.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These tree roles correspond to those of the wizard, the king and the
warrior that Tony Robbins used in his pattern of indirect negotiation
during an intervention at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rmtcenter.com/creating-leadership-in-times-of-crisis/"&gt;a seminar on september 11th 2001&lt;/a&gt;.
The only role that is missing is 'the fool'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fool is the only one that can redicule anyone, including the king,
and go unpunished. This role is crucial in limiting unrealistic ambitions,
yes-men and misleading advisors. With mild or not-so-mild humor he pulls
you back into reality, gets both your feet firmly on the ground and
maybe even slaps reality straight in your face.
The role of the fool is extremely underappreciated in a corporate culture
that relies on heavily paid consultants who do not dare to risk their precious
billable hours by pinching illusions and unrealistc ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A former manager of mine used this mantra:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
You are either part of the solution or part of the problem.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to oppose this with another observation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
If you cannot solve the problem you can still make good money by
prolonging it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still in many organisations external consultants are far better paid than
regular staff.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Rick Veenstra</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2013 11:20:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:localhost:8000,2013-01-26:2013/01/Every_successful_enterprise_requires_three_men/</guid><category>quotes</category></item></channel></rss>